Guide to the J. B. S. (Jacob Benjamin Salutsky) Hardman Papers TAM.050
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
J. B. S. (Jacob Benjamin Salutsky) Hardman Papers
1908-1970
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Hardman, J. B. S. (Jacob Benjamin Salutsky), 1882-1968
Hardman, Mrs. Virginia Mishnun
TAM.050
23.5 Linear Feet in 47 manuscript boxes and one oversize flat box.
J. B. S. (Jacob Benjamin Salutsky) Hardman (1882-1968) was a Russian-born author, social philosopher, and editor and leader who served the Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America as director of education and cultural activities and as editor of its organ, The Advance(1920-44). He also edited Naye Welt, a Yiddish-language socialist weekly, and American Labor Monthly. He organized the American Labor Press Association, and was chairman of the Inter-Union Institute for Labor and Democracy (publisher of Labor and Nation, which he founded and edited from 1944-1953). The papers contain correspondence (some in Russian and Yiddish), materials apparently collected for an unrealized autobiographical project titled, "Odyssey," other biographical materials, numerous drafts of published and unpublished writings, clippings, and files on his labor and political activities containing a mix of correspondence, internal documents and printed ephemera.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Mrs. Virginia Mishnun Hardman, 1971. The accession numbers associated with this gift are 1971.005 and 1971.006.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
J. B. S. (Jacob Benjamin Salutsky) Hardman (1882-1968) social philosopher, author, editor and leader in the development of American trade unionism for over sixty years, was born in Vilna in 1882. Because of his revolutionary and trade-union activities he was exiled in 1908. He came to the United States where he became active in the Socialist Party and the trade-union movement. He was editor of Naye Welt, a socialist weekly, and of American Labor Monthly, also a socialist-oriented journal, 1923-1924; director of education and cultural activities of the Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America for twenty-four years and editor of the union's official organ, The Advance. He organized and was president of the American Labor Press Association and served as chairman of the Inter-Union Institute for Labor and Democracy, the publisher of Labor and Nation, which he founded and edited from 1944-1953.
Sources:
J. B. S. Hardman, 1882-1968: Biographical Sketch, by Felicja Figa and Franklin L. Jonas ( Bulletin of the Tamiment Library, no. 48, March 1973, pp. 1-6).
Scope and Content Note
The papers contain personal correspondence (1908-1953), business correspondence (1925-1968), biographical material, writings by Hardman on labor and politics, manuscript and published articles by others sent to him for editorial comment, material on labor and political activities, and clippings on labor-related issues. Hardman was active in many organizations, including the Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America, Inter-Union Institute for Labor and Democracy, American Labor Press Association, Columbia University's Council for Research in the Social Sciences, Brookwood Labor College, the Jewish Socialist Federation, Workers Party of America, Conference for Progressive Labor Action, and other organizations. His work and activities within these organizations are documented in the collection.
Arrangement
Files are arranged alphabetically (sometimes by keyword) within each series, except for correspondence, which is arranged chronologically.
The files are grouped into six series:
Series I: Personal Correspondence
Series II: Biographical
Series III: Business Correspondence
Series IV: Writings
Series V: Labor and Political Activities
Series VI: Clippings
Files are arranged alphabetically (sometimes by keyword) within each series, except for correspondence, which is arranged chronologically.
The files are grouped into six series:
Missing Title
I, Personal Correspondence
II, Biographical
III, Business Correspondence
IV, Writings
V, Labor and Political Activities
VI, Clippings
Reports.; Manuscripts (document genre); Clippings (information artifacts); Minutes (administrative records); Articles.; Labor -- United States.; Socialism -- United States.; Correspondence.; Labor unions -- Political activity -- United States.; Labor unions -- United States.; Labor union journalism |z United States.; Jewish Socialist Federation of America; Workers Party (1940-1949); New York School of Philanthropy; Columbia University; Inter-Union Institute for Labor and Democracy; Conference for Progressive Labor Action; Roper, Elmo, 1900-1971.; Brookwood Labor College (Katonah, N.Y.); Deutsch, Babette, 1895-1982; American Workers Party; Ruthenberg, Charles E. (Charles Emil), 1882-1927; American Labor Press Association; Mills, C. Wright (Charles Wright), 1916-1962; Lore, Ludwig.; Muste, Abraham John, 1885-1967.; Frank, Waldo David, 1889-1967; Hardman, J. B. S. (Jacob Benjamin Salutsky), 1882-1968; Harris, Louis.; Ickes, Harold L. (Harold LeClair), 1874-1952; Perlman, Selig, 1888-; Postgate, Raymond, 1896-1971; Dewey, John, 1859-1952.; Thomas, Norman, 1884-1968; Socialist Party (U.S.); Murray, Philip, 1886-1952.; Hardman, Mrs. Virginia Mishnun
- Series I: Personal Correspondence, 1910-1967
  Scope and Content Note
  Early personal correspondence, much of it in Russian and Yiddish, is with family members, including Hardman's wife, Hannah Goldenstein Hardman. Later correspondence with Louis Corey, Babette Deutsch, John Dewey, Waldo Frank, and C. E. Ruthenberg relates chiefly to Hardman's writing and editorial activities for the Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America (1920-1944).
  - Personal Correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Personal Correspondence, Jan 1912 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Personal Correspondence, Feb 1912 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Personal Correspondence, Mar 1912-Aug 1912 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Personal Correspondence, Oct 1912-Dec 1912 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Personal Correspondence, Jan 1913-May 1913 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Personal Correspondence, Apr 1913-May 1913 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Personal Correspondence, Jun 1913-Jul 1913 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Personal Correspondence, Aug 1913 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Personal Correspondence, Sep 1913-Nov 1913 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1914-1918 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1919 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1920 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1921 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Personal Correspondence, Jan 1922-Apr 1922 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Personal Correspondence, May 1922-Dec 1922 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1923 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1924 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1926 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1928 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1929 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1930 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1931 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1932 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1933 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1934 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1935 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1937 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1938 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1940-1942 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1943-1947, 1949, 1951 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1953 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1962-1967 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Series II: Biographical, 1908-1973
  Biographical material includes many topical files of material (including correspondence, speeches, notes, etc.) apparently gathered by Hardman for an unrealized autobiographical project, entitled "Odyssey," and files on Hardman's family and his early life, his associations with Amalgamated Clothing Workers, Brookwood Labor College (1932-1933), and the Jewish Socialist Federation (1920-1921).
  - Documents, Personal (name change, naturalization, Russian passport), 1908-1909, 1924, 1953, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Obituaries and Letters of Condolences, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Odyssey Files Files: Jewish Socialist Federation-Financial Matters, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Odyssey Files: Correspondence, 1920-1956 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Odyssey Files: Amalgamated Clothing Workers-Hardman Speeches, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Odyssey Files: Amalgamated Clothing Workers-Hardman Speeches, 1922-1944 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Odyssey Files: American Labor Monthly, 1923 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Odyssey Files: Brookwood Labor College, undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Odyssey Files: Personal Correspondence (in Russian and Yiddish), ca.1909-1946 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Odyssey Files: C.I.O.-New York State Radio, Press, and Education Committee, undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Odyssey Files: Oral History Transcript (for Columbia University, with correspondence and notes), 1962-1963 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Odyssey Files: Family Matters, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Odyssey Files: Mrs. Hannah Hardman, undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Odyssey Files: Diary Notes, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Odyssey Files: Book Contracts and Correspondence re: Publishing, undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Odyssey Files: Documentary Manuscripts (Biographical Notes), undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Odyssey Files: Documentary Manuscripts (Biographical Notes), undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Odyssey Files: Encyclopedia of Social Sciences, undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Testimonial Dinner (material from scrapbook), Nov 17, 1942 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Union Membership Cards and Other Memorabilia, undated (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Series III: Business Correspondence, 1925-1970
  In the course of his work as chairman of the Inter-Union Institute he corresponded with Harold L. Ickes, Ludwig Lore, C. Wright Mills, Philip Murray, A. J. Muste, Selig Perlman, and Raymond Postgate, among others. Other correspondence reflects his work as editor of Labor and Nation (1945-1953), as president of the American Labor Press Association during World War II, and as research director of the Labor Leadership Study sponsored by Columbia University's Council for Research in the Social Sciences (1949-1960).
  - Business Correspondence (2 letters), 1925 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Business Correspondence (2 letters), 1930, 1932 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Business Correspondence (2 letters), 1934 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Business Correspondence (2 letters), 1939 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Business Correspondence (15 letters), 1940 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Business Correspondence (8 letters), 1941 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Business Correspondence (4 letters), 1942-1943 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Business Correspondence (14 letters), 1944 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Business Correspondence (37 letters), 1945 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Business Correspondence (68 letters), 1946 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Business Correspondence (19 letters), 1947 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Business Correspondence (14 letters), 1948 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Business Correspondence (88 letters), 1949 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Business Correspondence (124 letters), 1950 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Business Correspondence (181 letters), 1951 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Business Correspondence (120 letters), 1952 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Business Correspondence re: Labor and Nation Proposal, 1952 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Business Correspondence (87 letters), 1953 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Business Correspondence (95 letters), 1954 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Business Correspondence (37 letters), 1955 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Business Correspondence (19 letters), 1956 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Business Correspondence (27 letters), 1957 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Business Correspondence (53 letters), 1958 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Business Correspondence (28 letters), 1959 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Business Correspondence (26 letters), 1960 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Business Correspondence (65 letters), 1961 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Business Correspondence (27 letters), 1962 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Business Correspondence (36 letters), 1963 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Business Correspondence (33 letters), 1964 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Business Correspondence (59 letters), 1965 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Business Correspondence (35 letters), 1966 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Business Correspondence (29 letters), 1967 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Business Correspondence, 1968-1970 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Business Correspondence (23 letters), undated (Box 10, Folder 8)
- Series IV: Writings, 1910-1970
  This series contains articles, manuscripts, and other writings written by Hardman. It also includes writings by others with commentary by Hardman.
  - The Activist Minority, undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - AFL-CIO Convention: Two Years after the Merger, undated (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - An American Federation That Might Be (published), undated (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - American Labor Dynamic (outline), undated (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - American Labor Ten Years Hence (outline), undated (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - American Labor in Profile, Labor Examiner, undated (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - American Labor in Profile (manuscript), undated (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - American Labor Movement, undated (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - American Labor Movement in Profile (list of selected essays), undated (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - American Unionism in Retrospect, undated (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - American Union Movement: History of the Movement (part 1), undated (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - American Union Movement: History of the Movement (part 2), undated (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - American Workers Party, 1934 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Anti-Intellectualism, 1966 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Anxious Decades, undated (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Anxious Decades, 1950 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Articles/Clippings, 1918-1953 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Articles/Clippings, 1923-1947 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Articles Prepared for and Published in Selected Works, 1925-1945 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Articles Prepared for and Published in Selected Works, undated (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Articles Prepared for and Published in Selected Works, undated (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Articles: In Yiddish, undated (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Articles: Various Periodicals, undated (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - The Balance Sheet, undated (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Bibliography: Miscellaneous Notices and Reviews, undated (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Black and White: John L. Lewis, undated (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Blueprints on Shifting Sands?, undated (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Changing Fashions in Collective Bargaining, undated (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Blueprints for the Great American Revolution, undated (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Bluff, But Moderately, undated (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Changing Fashions in Labor Politics, undated (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Choose Your Way, undated (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - C.I.O.: Beginnings (published), undated (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - C.I.O.: The First Ten Years (published), undated (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - C.I.O. Proper, undated (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Collective Bargaining, 1954 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Collective Bargaining: Rackets and Ethics, 1954 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Communism in America, undated (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - A Conference to End All Conferences, undated (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Consciousness of Kind, undated (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Corruption, Dishonesty, and Violence, undated (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Crisis of Culture, undated (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Crisis in Our Time, undated (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Date with Destiny, undated (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Democracy in Action, undated (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - David Dubinsky: Labor Leader and Man, undated (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - David Dubinsky: Doctor of Laws, undated (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Dubinsky Negatives, undated (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Debs, undated (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - The Demands for Regulation of Labor, undated (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Decade: 30-60, undated (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Decades of Hope Deferred, 1920 (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - Decade of Tension, undated (Box 15, Folder 13)
  - Depression Hits the USA, Jan 7, 1931 (Box 15, Folder 14)
  - Dilemma of a Depressed Bourgeois, undated (Box 15, Folder 15)
  - Dinner, A.L.E.S.: Honoring Esther Peterson (Asst. Secretary of Labor), Feb 18, 1961 (Box 15, Folder 16)
  - Discussion Notes-Observation (seminar), 1955 (Box 15, Folder 17)
  - Drafts, Sep 18, 1966 (Box 15, Folder 18)
  - Drafts, undated (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Dynamic of American Trade Unionism, undated (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Economist Meeting, May 31, 1946 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - The Elite (Base), undated (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - En-Route to U.S., 1965-1967 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Evolving Pattern of the American Revolution, Mar 1933 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Fascistomania (drafts, published), Jun 9, 1967 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Federation Faces the Facts, Dec 21, 1932 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Fine Art of Unionism (drafts), 1929 (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Fifty Years of American Labor, Oct 11, 1931 (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Footnotes to the IBT Profile, undated (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Freedom in a Functional Society, undated (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Genealogy of Labor Radicalism, undated (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Girl Organizer Reports, undated (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Great Divide, undated (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - William D. Haywood, undated (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Sidney Hillman (CIO), undated (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - How the Local Union Lives, undated (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Ideas (Documentary), undated (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Inchin' Along, undated (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - Influences Changing Democracy, undated (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - Intellectual Inventory, undated (Box 17, Folder 12)
  - Intellectual Rebellion, undated (Box 17, Folder 13)
  - Internal Union Democracy-in Profile, undated (Box 17, Folder 14)
  - Inter-Relationship of the Jewish and the General American Labor Movements, 1950, 1953 (Box 17, Folder 15)
  - Internal Union Democracy, Jun 1961 (Box 17, Folder 16)
  - Internal Union Democracy, undated (Box 17, Folder 17)
  - Internal Union Democracy, undated (Box 17, Folder 18)
  - Internal Union Democracy, undated (Box 17, Folder 19)
  - Internal Union Democracy (Ford-special pages), undated (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Internal Union Democracy, undated (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Internal Union Democracy, undated (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Internal Union Democracy, undated (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Internal Union Democracy (copy-final text), Jun 1961 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Intra-Union Research: The Aim and the Means, 1957, 1963 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Industrial Relations Research Association Spring Meeting: Boston, MA, May 2, 1959 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Is a Labor Party on the Way?, undated (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Is a New Party Possible?, May 11, 1933 (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - Jewish and Non-Jewish Influences Which Helped Shape the Course of the Jewish Labor Movement in the United States, Dec 1962 (Box 18, Folder 10)
  - Wings in Needledom: Issues Behind Factional Conflict in the Clothing Industry, 1960 (Box 18, Folder 11)
  - Labor and the Immigrants, undated (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Labor-Capital Cooperation, undated (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Labor's Anxious Decades, Mar 25, 1963 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Labor's Anxious Decades (documentary), Sep 17, 1962 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Labor Intellectuals, 1927-1933 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Labor Dynamics, 1936 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Labor Imperialism, undated (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Labor in Midpassage, Harvard Business Review, 1953 (Box 19, Folder 7a)
  - Labor in Retrospect (typed copy), Oct 30, 1961-Nov 1, 1961 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Labor Leadership in the Unions and Society, undated (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Labor Movement, Oct 21, 1963 (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - Labor Leader Study, undated (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - The Labor Movement (ideas), Jul 17, 1956 (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - Labor Movement and the Radicals, undated (Box 19, Folder 13)
  - Labor Movement in a Changing World, undated (Box 19, Folder 14)
  - Labor Movement-The Public and Defense (panel discussion), Apr 5, 1941 (Box 19, Folder 15)
  - Labor's Non-Partisan League, Nov 5, 1936 (Box 19, Folder 16)
  - Labor on the Warpath?, Aug 31, 1932 (Box 19, Folder 17)
  - Labor Politics, Jun 23, 1951 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Labor Racketeering, Apr 28, 1932 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Labor Relations in the Next Decade, undated (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Labor's Civil War, undated (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Labor's Road to Power, Dec 1929 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - LaFollette: Tennessee (report), undated (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Last Words of Sacco and Vanzetti, Aug 1927 (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - Late 40's-50's, 1962-1963 (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - Late Lamented American Labor Party, undated (Box 20, Folder 9)
  - Leadership, 1970 (Box 20, Folder 10)
  - Leadership of John L. Lewis, undated (Box 20, Folder 11)
  - Lectures, Pamphlets, 1947, 1956-1957 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Leadership Study, undated (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Legislating Union Democracy, Dec 2, 1957 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - John L. Lewis as a Labor Leader and Man, undated (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - John L. Lewis of the United Mine Workers of America, undated (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - John L. Lewis-Synthesis of a Labor Empire Builder, undated (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Lemke's Union Party, undated (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - Limited and/or Inclusive Unionism, undated (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - Limits of Unionism (drafts), 1967 (Box 21, Folder 9)
  - Lists of Articles, undated (Box 21, Folder 10)
  - Living and Leading in a Time of Crisis, undated (Box 21, Folder 11)
  - Living With Crisis (published), undated (Box 21, Folder 12)
  - Madison (manuscript and notes), undated (Box 21, Folder 13)
  - Making of a Rebel, Dec 28, 1967 (Box 21, Folder 14)
  - Manpower (master copy), 1964-1965 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - McClellan Committee Report, undated (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - Memorandum: To the Finance Board of the New York Joint Board-ACWA, Jun 11, 1965 (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - 24-Million White-Collar Workers: Labor's Achilles Heel-and Hope, Nov 21, 1965 (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - Memo: To Norman Thomas, Dec 21, 1951 (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - Mooney Was Justly Convicted, undated (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - Philip Murray as Labor Leader, undated (Box 22, Folder 7)
  - National and Personal Security, 1962 (Box 22, Folder 8)
  - Needle-Trades Union: A Labor Movement at 50, Social Research, 1960 (Box 22, Folder 9)
  - Needle Trades Unions: Misc. Drafts, undated (Box 22, Folder 10)
  - New Leader Pieces, 1957-1960 (Box 22, Folder 11)
  - Not Born Yesterday, undated (Box 22, Folder 12)
  - Notes: Debs, undated (Box 22, Folder 13)
  - Notes, Drafts, 1964 (Box 22, Folder 14)
  - Notes on Labor Leader Arguables, 1954-1967 (Box 22, Folder 15)
  - Notes on Neo-Communism, 1954-1955 (Box 22, Folder 16)
  - Ole and Ezra as Social Engineers, 1931 (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - Perlman's Labor Theater, undated (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - Not All's Quiet on the Left, undated (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - Organized Labor, undated (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - Outline of Introduction, undated (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - The Passing of a Faith, undated (Box 23, Folder 6)
  - Our Hope-Labor and Democracy, undated (Box 23, Folder 7)
  - Organized Labor (drafts, suggestions), undated (Box 23, Folder 8)
  - Oneness-Classes, 1948 (Box 23, Folder 9)
  - A Not-Impossible Utopia, May 22, 1931 (Box 23, Folder 10)
  - Oral History (incomplete), undated (Box 23, Folder 11)
  - Organized Labor, undated (Box 23, Folder 12)
  - Perspectives of the American Revolutionary Movement, undated (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Wanted: A Philosophy of the American Labor Movement, undated (Box 24, Folder 2)